A Guide to the Records of Governor Kaine's Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities, 2002-2009
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of Governor Kaine's Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities, 2002-2009
The Library of Virginia
44697
7 cubic feet (20 Boxes)
Community Integration for People with Disabilities, Office of
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Office of Governor Kaine on 14 January 2010.
Historical Information
A 1999 decision of the U.S. Supreme Court in Olmstead v. L.C., found that the segregation of persons with disabilities constituted discrimination in violation of Title II of the Americans with Disabilities Act. As prescribed by this decision, compliance required that individuals with disabilities receive services in the most integrated setting appropriate to their needs, so that people with disabilities could become as fully integrated in the community as they chose to be. Following the Supreme Court decision, Governor Mark Warner convened the Virginia Olmstead Task Force in 2002. In their One Community report, this 70 member Task Force laid out a vision of Virginia becoming one community for people with disabilities that included 201 recommendations for individual choice of and access to services and supports; sufficient numbers of qualified providers; safe, available, accessible, and affordable housing and transportation; an opportunity to work; a full continuum of care, from self care through institutional care; and accountability to everyone. Julie Stanley was named director of the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities in 2004.
Governor Warner's Executive Order 61 (2004) provided for the infrastructure and process to continue the work that the Task Force began by creating a four cabinet-member, 18 state agency Community Integration Implementation Team, a 19 member stakeholder Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee, and a Director of the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities. The Community Integration Implementation Team was charged with completing cost out and updates to the 201 recommendations in One Community, the Report of the Olmstead Task Force; working to ensure collaborative efforts to complete and annually update a comprehensive cross-governemental strategic plan designed to ensure continued community integration, and to annually report to the Governor on accomplishments. The Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee was tasked with overseeing the implementation of of the Olmstead v. L.C. decision in Virginia; advising the Community Integration Implementation Team and receiving their reports; and preparing reports making recommendations to the Governor. They were also responsible for monitoring the implementation of state and federal laws concerning community integration of Virginians with disabilities; studying all matters that present barriers or challenges to full community integration; and advising and making recommendations to the Director and Implementation Team and reviewing and advising them on the strategic plan. Executive Order 84 (2005) continued the implementation of the Olmstead Initiative.
Governor Kaine continued the Olmstead initiative with the issuance of Executive Order 2 (2006) and directed the Community Integration Implementation Team to work with stakeholder groups to develop a cross-governmental strategic plan for community integration, with input from the Community Integration Oversight Advisory Board. Also in 2006, the General Assembly codified the advisory group as the Community Integration Advisory Commission (SB 182, 2006) within the exectuive branch to monitor the progress of all executive branch agencies toward community integration of Virginians with disabilities in accordance with all applicable state and federal laws and to make appropriate recommnedations to the Governor (Code of Virginia 2.2-2524). In 2007, Governor Kaine issued Executive Directive 6, which directed state agencies and entities to continue their collaborative efforts to complete the implementation of the Olmstead initiative and to annually complete and update a comprehensive, cross-governmental strategic plan and report to the Governor on the progress of implementation.
Scope and Content
The records document the work of the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities, the Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee/Board, and the Community Integration Implementation Team to review and cost out the Virginia Olmstead Task Force recommendations and develop a comprehensive cross-governmental strategic plan for community integration. These records include correspondence, legislative files, meeting records and minutes, presentations, reports and subject files.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Director's correspondence and subject files, 2004-2009
Series II. Legislation, 2004-2009
Series III. Meetings, 2005-2008
Series IV. Presentations, 2003-2009
Series V. Olmstead Task Force Recommendations, 2004-2005
Series VI. Reports, 2004-2005.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and subject files, 2004-2009., Extent: 6 boxes (2.1 cu. ft.). (Box 1-6)
  Director's correspondence and subject files, 2004-2009, are housed in 6 boxes and arranged alphabetically. Includes correspondence, as well as cost reports, executive orders, notes, plans, programs, reports and studies. Topical files cover education, employment, executive orders, grants, housing, independent living, mental health, Olmstead Task Force recommendations, reporting, strategic planning, training, transportation, and both the Community Integration Implementation Team and Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee.
  - General correspondence, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General correspondence, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General correspondence, 2006. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General correspondence, 2007. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General correspondence, 2008. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bolin, Barbara - Special Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Development, 2004. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Conference on Emergency Management and Individuals with Disabilites and the Elderly, 2006 June 28-30. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cost Out Reports - EO84, 204. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dementia, 2002. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Disabilities, Virginia Board for People with, 2003-2005. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Education Campaign, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Executive Order 84-1 Membership, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Executive Order 84-2a Nursing Facility Wait Lists, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Executive Order 84-5 Reporting System, 2005. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Housing Issues Report, 2003. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Implementation Status Report - Documentation for General Initiatives, 2002-2005. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Implementation Team, 2004. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Independent Living Council, Virginia Statewide, 2001. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Reporting, 2005 Oct 20. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mental Health Transformation State Incentive Grant, 2005. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, undated. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Non-IT Agencies, 2004. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Olmstead Employment Issues Team, 2002-2003. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Oversight Advisory Committee, 2004-2005. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Phase II Recommendations, 2004-2005. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Public Feedback, 2004. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rail and Public Transportation, 2005-2006. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Real Choice Systems Change Grants, 2004. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Strategic Planning, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Strategic Planning, 2004-2005. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Strategic Planning (1.1 and 1.2), 208. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Strategic Planning (4.1, 4.2, and 4.3), undated. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Strategic Planning - Auxiliary Grant Portability (7.2F), 2008. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Strategic Plan - Cross-Governmental Strategic Plan to Governor, 2007 Aug. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Strategic Plan - Local Government Responses to Cross-Governmental Strategic Plan, 2007. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Stratetic Plan - Local Government VALHSO meeting, 2007. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Strategic Planning - Small Group Facilitators, 2008 Aug. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Choosing Providers (part I), 2006. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Choosing Providers (part II), 2006. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2)- Choosing Self-Direction (part I), 2006. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Choosing Self-Direction (part II), 2006. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Housing (part I), 2006. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Housing (part II), 2006. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Housing (part III), 2006. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Housing (part IV), 2006. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Ongoing Community Support (part I), 2006. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Ongoing Community Support (part II), 2006. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Surrogate Decision Making, 2006. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Success Factors, 2006. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Task Force and Oversight Advisory Committee Vision (EO2) - Transportation, 2006. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Team Member Designations, 2006-2008. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Training, 2006 Mar 30. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Series II. Legislation, 2004-2009., Extent: 2 boxes (.7 cubic feet). (Box 7-8)
  Legislation files, 2004-2009, are housed in 2 boxes and are arranged chronologically. These files track legislation that is of interest to the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities and include drafts of bills and bill tracking spreadsheets, as well as calendars, correspondence, committee meeting agendas, presentations and talking points, reports, and miscellaneous notes.
  - Legislative Session - Budget Amendments, 2004. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Legislative Session - Budget Priorities, 2004-2005. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Legislative Session - Impact, 2004. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Legislative Session - Licensing Proposal, 2004. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Legislative Session - Olmstead Budget Issues, 2004. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Legislative Session, 2005. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Legislative Session - Aging Action Task Force (Assisted Living Facilities), 2005. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Legislative Session - House and Senate Reports, 2005. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Legislative Session - Olmstead Task Force Recommendations, 2005. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Legislative Session, 2006. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Legislative Session, 2006. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Legislation, 2006. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Legislation - Community Integration Related Initiatives / Governor's Budget, 2006. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Legislation - Health and Human Resources Initiatives, 2006. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Legislation - Joint Commission on Healthcare, 2006. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Legislation - Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse, 2006. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Legislation - Olmstead, 2006. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Legislation - Virginia Disability Commission, 2006. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Legislative Session, 2007. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Legislative Session, 2009. (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Series III. Meetings, 2004-2008., Extent: 3 boxes (1.4 cubic feet). (Box 9-11)
  Meeting records, 2004-2008, are housed in two boxes and are arranged chronologically. Contains records for the Community Integration Implementation Team and the Community Integration Advisory Commission (previously the Olmstead Initiative Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee), as well as joint meetings of the two bodies. Includes agendas, articles, correspondence, minutes, notes, presentations, reports, sign-in sheets and strategic planning working papers. This collection also includes audio recordings for some of the meetings - audio tape list is available in receipt file. Please contact Archives Reference if you would like to use these tapes, as special arrangements will need to be made.
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team, 2004 July 27. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Meeting - Olmstead Initiative Oversight Advisory Committee - New Member Orientation, 2005 Mar 9. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Meeting - Olmstead Initiative Joint Meeting of the Community Integration Implementation Team and the Community Integration Oversight Committee, 2005 Mar 22. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Meeting - Olmstead Initiative Oversight Advisory Committee, 2005 Apr 19. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Meeting - Olmstead Initiative Community Integration Implementation Team, 2005 Apr 26. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Meeting - Olmstead Initiative Joint Meeting of the Community Integration Implementation Teadm and the Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee, 2005 May 24. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Meeting - Olmstead Initiative Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee, 2005 June 16. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Meeting - Olmstead Initiative Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee, 2005 July 26. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Meeting - Olmstead Initiative Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee, 2005 Aug 11. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Meeting - Olmstead Initiative Joint Meeting of the Community Integration Implementation Team and the Community Integration Oversight Advisory Committee, 2005 Aug 23. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Meeting - Virginia Disability Commission, 2005 Sept 21. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Meeting - Olmstead Initiative Community Integration Implementation Team, 2005 Oct 25. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Meeting - Virginia Disability Commission, 2005 Nov 16. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Oversight Advisory Board, 2006 Mar 7. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Oversight Advisory Board, 2006 Apr 6. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Meeting - Virginia Disability Commission (Housing Workshop), 2006 Apr 17. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team, 2006 May 2. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team, 2006 Aug 22. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Advisory Commission, 2006 Sept 8. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Advisory Commission, 2006 Sept 19. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team - Executive Committee, 2006 Sept 25. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team, 2006 Oct 17. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Advisory Commission, 2006 Oct 31. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Meeting - Small Group #1 Conference Call, 2006 Dec 8. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team, 2006 Dec 19. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Meeting - Small Group #1, 2007 Jan 10. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Advisory Commission, 2007 Mar 6. (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team, 2007 Mar 20. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team - New Member Orientation, 2007 May 29. (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Meeting - Joint Meeting of the Community Integration Advisory Commission and the Community Integration Implementation Team, 2007 June 19. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Meeting - Small Group #3 (Housing), 2007 July 23. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Meeting - Joint Meeting of the Community Integration Advisory Commission and the Community Integration Implementation Team, 2007 Aug 2. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Advisory Commission, 2007 Sept 11. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team, 2007 Sept 18. (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Meeting - Small Group #1, 2007 Nov 16. (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Meeting - Small Group #3 (Housing), 2007 Nov 20. (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Meeting - Small Group (Housing and Transportation), 2007 Dec 11. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team, 2007 Dec 18. (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Meeting - Miscellaneous sign-in sheets, 2007. (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Advisory Commission, 2008 Apr 1. (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team - Housing and Transportation (Small Group #3), 2008 May 9. (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team - Direct Support Professionals and Employment (Small Group #2), 2008 May 22. (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Adviory Commission, 2008 May 30. (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team - Ongoing Support (Small Group #1), 2008 June 16. (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Meeting - Executive Directive 6 Implementation Team, 2008 June 24. (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Implementation Team - Housing and Transportation (Small Group #3), 2008 July 25. (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Advisory Commission, 2008 July 29. (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Meeting - Community Integration Advisory Commission, 2008 Oct 21. (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Meeting - Executive Directive 6 Implementation Team, 2008 Dec 16. (Box 11, Folder 22)
- Series IV. Presentations, 2003-2009., Extent: 3 boxes (1.4 cubic feet). (Box 12-14)
  Presentations, 2003-2009, are housed in 3 boxes and are arranged chronologically. The majority of the presentations are by Director Julie Stanley, though some presentations by others are included as well. Presentations were made to the legislature, commissions, boards, and various others groups, as well as at conferences, and address the work of the Office of Community Integration for People with Disabilities and issues faced by those with disabilities and their families. Includes speeches, presentation slides, notes, meeting agendas, talking points, and conference materials and programs. Folders are identified by organization being addressed.
  - Presentation - House Appropriations - Health and Human Resources Subcommittee, 2003 Sept 15. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Presentation - Joint Commission on Healthcare, 2003 Sept 17. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Presentation - Employment Collaboration Conference, 2003 Sept 29. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Presentation - Virginia Disability Commission, 2003 Sept 30. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Presentation - ARC of Northern Shenandoah Valley, 2003 Nov 3. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Presentation - Lord Fairfax Providers Association, 2003 Nov 5. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Presentation - Assistant Directors of Administration, 2003 Dec 10. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Presentation - Virginia Disability Commission, 2004 Jan 15. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Presentation - Senate Finance - Health and Human Resources Subcommittee, 2004 Jan 19. (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Presentation - House Appropriations Committee, 2004 Jan 21. (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Presentation - State Human Rights Committee, 2004 Mar 5. (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Presentation - Virginia Board for People with Disabilities, 2004 Mar 26. (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Presentation - ARC of Northern Shenandoah Valley, 2004 Mar 27. (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Presentation - Virginia Guardianship Association and Virginia Elder Rights Coalition Conference, 2004 Apr-5. (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Presentation - John Tyler Community College, 2004 June 2. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Presentation - KOVAR Summer Institute, 2004 July 2. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Presentation - Annual Conference on Disabilities, 2004 Oct 18. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Presentation - Virginia Disability Commission, 2004 Oct 29. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Presentation - Fourth Annual Special Needs Symposium, 2004 Nov 4. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Presentation - Community-Based Services, Inc., 2004 Nov 22. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Presentation - Virginia Disability Commission, 2004 Dec 17. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Presentation - Virginia Association of Centers of Independent Living, 2005 June 9. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Presentation - Virginia's Public Guardian Programs, 2005 June 10. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Presentation - Insight Enterprises, Inc. / Peninsula Center for Independent Living Annual Conference on Disabilities, 2005 Oct 17. (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Presentation - Virginia Disability Commission, 2005 Nov 16. (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Presentation - Resources for Independent Living, 2006 May 9. (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Presentation - Joint National Conference on Mental Health Block Grants and National Conference on Mental Health Statistics, 2006 June 1. (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Presentation - Virginia Housing Coalition, 200 June 22. (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Presentation - Virginia Independent Living Conference - Developing Dynamic Disability Leadership, 2006 Aug 28-29. (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Presentation - Richmond Commons: When Sirens Sound - Policy, Research and Equity in Regional Emergency Planning, 2007 Feb 15. (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Presentation - Commonwealth Autism Service 6th Annual Conference, 2007 Mar 8. (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Presentation - Virginia Transition Forum, 2007 Mar 12. (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Presentation - Falls Church Long-Term Care Coordinating Council, 2007 May 9. (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Presentation - Virginia Disability Commission, 2007 Aug 13. (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Presentation - Virginia Association of Area Agencies on Aging, 2008 Jan 22. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Presentation - Virginia Association of Local Human Services Officials Conference, 2008 Feb 6. (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Presentation - Virginia Transition Forum, 2008 Mar 17-19. (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Presentation - Virginia Guardianship Association and Elder Rights and Disability Services Joint Conference, 2008 Apr 8. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Presentation - Virginia Alliance of Socail Work Practitioners, 2008 May 7. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Presentation - Virginia Coalition for the Prevention of Elder Abuse, 2008 May 29-30. (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Presentation - Virginia Association of Housing and Community Development Officials, 2008 June 26. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Presentation - Virginia Disability Commission, 2009 Oct 22. (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Presentation - Statewide Independent Living Council, 2009 Nov 4-5. (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Presentation - Your Life, Your Choice, Your Home, undated. (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Series V. Olmstead Task Force Recommendations, 2004-2005., Extent: 5 boxes (1.75 cubic feet). (Box 15-19)